<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<title>Documentation</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>What this is about</title>
			<para>
				This document serves as a mingle-mangle of thoughts about
				the game we're developing including goals, brainstorming, protocols of
				progress, architectural designs and anything that should be kept in
				mind. Feel free to add anything that in your opinion should be
				mentioned here. After consultation with other developers involved in
				the project, change parts of the documentation to fit to new ideas, but
				please <emphasis>DO NOT SIMPLY ERASE DOCUMENTATION THAT IS OUT OF DATE!
				</emphasis> Instead you should mark obsolete documentation by scratching
				out the text. 
			</para>
	</section>
	
	
	<section>
		<title>What we aim for</title>
			<para>
				This project is about developing a multiplayer game appropiate to be
				played competitively as an eSport title. For us, a successful eSport title
				is characterized by:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Many players:</emphasis> A successful eSports game needs
						to have a lot of players. For example Counter-Strike had been the #1
						(competitive) multiplayer game for years and thus was found on many
						LANs and tournaments although it did not serve a spectator-friendly
						environment. But because of that it was not able to bring eSports to
						such a high level of acceptance and interest as it is nowadays. This
						leads to the following point.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Many spectators:</emphasis> 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A deep sportive characteristic
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

		<section>
			<title>Many players</title>
				<para>
					To achieve a huge amount of players the game must fulfill the following
					properties:
				</para>
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Easy to learn:</emphasis>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	
	</section>
</article>