<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<title>Documentation</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>What this is about</title>
			<para>
				This document serves as a mingle-mangle of thoughts about
				the game we're developing including goals, brainstorming, protocols of
				progress, architectural designs and anything that should be kept in
				mind. Feel free to add anything that in your opinion should be
				mentioned here. After consultation with other developers involved in
				the project, change parts of the documentation to fit to new ideas, but
				please <emphasis>DO NOT SIMPLY ERASE DOCUMENTATION THAT IS OUT OF DATE!
				</emphasis> Instead you should mark obsolete documentation by scratching
				out the text. 
			</para>
	</section>
	
	
	<section>
		<title>What we aim for</title>
			<para>
				This project is about developing a multiplayer game appropiate to be
				played competitively as an eSport title. For us, a successful eSport title
				is characterized by:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Many players:</emphasis> A successful eSports game needs
						to have a lot of players. For example Counter-Strike had been the #1
						(competitive) multiplayer game for years and thus was found on many
						LANs and tournaments although it did not serve a spectator-friendly
						environment. But because of that it was not able to bring eSports to
						such a high level of acceptance and interest as it is nowadays. This
						leads to the following point.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Many spectators:</emphasis> Spectators are very important
						for the success of a (e)sport. You may realize this by thinking of
						the success of 1on1 first-person-shooters like Painkiller or Quake.
						Especially Painkiller had a relativly small community of active players 
						but achieved being shown on MTV since people like watching it.
						Nowadays, titles like League Of Legends and StarCraft2 combine both,
						many players and many spectators, and thus brought eSports to a
						new level.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>A deep sportive characteristic:</emphasis> An eSports title
						must show up with a high level of sportive competition meaning that
						there should be least dependency on luck and various approches to win
						so no match looks like another. This is what World Of Warcraft was
						missed to become a big eSport title although there were an impressive
						amount of players and spectators.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

		<section>
			<title>Many players</title>
				<para>
					To achieve a huge amount of players the game must fulfill the following
					properties:
				</para>
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Easy to learn:</emphasis> A game must be easy to learn
							so it does not scare off players that are new to the game.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Innovation:</emphasis> There should be a high degree of
							new elements that have not been seen in other games to make it
							more interesting.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Popular genre:</emphasis> Although there must be innovation
							the game should belong to a popular genre. For example, farming simulation
							is not appropriate here.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Low hardware requirements:</emphasis> To make it available
							for as many people as possible, there should be little hardware
							requirements so it can be played on almost any hardware.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Portability</emphasis> Because of the same argument as for
							low hardware requirements, the game should be available for any (common)
							platform.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Many spectators</title>
				<para>
					To achieve a huge amount of spectators the game must fulfill the following
					properties:
				</para>
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Easy to learn/understand</emphasis> As for players, the spectator
							must be able to get into the game easily. Complicated rules scare them off.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Various possibilities of watching</emphasis> People must be able
							to tune in to matches anytime and anywhere so there must be different ways
							of gaining information about matches.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Deep sportive characteristic</title>
				<para>
					To achieve a deep sportive characteristic the game must fulfill the following
					properties:
				</para>
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Little impact of luck:</emphasis> There should be little impact of
							luck since luck falsifies players' real skill and makes a match's result random.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>High degree of competition:</emphasis> Players must be given the
							ressources and institutions to compete with each other.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Balance:</emphasis> There must be good game-balance. Otherwise
							strategies or certain approches will lead to a domination in the game making
							it boring to watch and play.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				
				</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	
	</section>
	
</article>
