<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Game launcher, menu and matchmaking</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
	    <title>General structure</title>
	    <para>
	        Users play the game with a game client. When client starts, it checkes for updates and then prompts user for login.
	        The User can use the client to configure their preferences and profile, start matches with friends and spectate or review other matches.  
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Authentication</title>
	    <para>
	        Players need to authenticate to play the game. To login they need a unique username (account name) and a password.
	        An authentication can be successful only when game client version matches server version.
	    </para>
        <para>
	        To authenticate, players need to have an account. Account registration is done either in game client directly or on our website.
	        To register, a valid e-mail address is required to verify your account.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Profiles</title>
        <para>
            Each user has a user profile where he can select a profile picture and a displayname for custom games (in tournaments your account name is used always).
            In your profile you can see your results of recent matches and replay most recent matches.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Chatting</title>
        <para>
            Chatting between users is also available while not playing. In order to find partners and group up this is a very useful feature.
            Chat partners are addressed by their account name.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Friendlist</title>
        <para>
            
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
	    <title>Settings</title>
	    <table>
            <title>Profile settings</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Setting name</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                        <entry>possible values</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            Profile picture
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            Allows the player to select a profile picture that is displayed next to its name (ingame and in matchmaking).
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            list of profile-pictures 
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            Display name
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            Player can choose a unique displayname. If a game is marked as private, users can choose any name before game starts.
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            (textbox)
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>Privacy settings</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Setting name</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                        <entry>possible values</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            Online status
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            If set to hidden, user is displayed as offline to other users.
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            Online, Want to play, Away, Busy, Do not disturb, Hidden 
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>Game settings</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Setting name</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                        <entry>possible values</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                   
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
	</section>
</article>