<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<title>Gameplay</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
	    <title>Game setting and goal</title>
	    <para>
			Two teams fight against on a large map. Each team consists of a maximum of 5 players.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	        The first team that destroys enemy base wins.
	    </para>
	    </section>
	<section>
		<title>General game cycle</title>
			<para>
			    Both teams start randomly at either top-left or bottom-right corner of map (yes, this is contrary to common multiplayer maps like LOL. That's intended.).
			    Teams spread into the map trying to conquer neutral bases that are spread all over the map. Then they will move forward to enemy base.
			</para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Neutral bases</title>
	    <para>
	        Neutral bases can be conquered by a team. Once a base is conquered it should be defended against enemy team.
	        If defence fails, enemy team can conquer the neutral base to optain its benefits.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	        Neutral bases consist of a tower surrounded by some buildings. The tower provides some basic vision (see advantages) and is the central key of the base.
	        A player can conquer a base by right-clicking its tower and channeling until control switched to his team. An already conquered base must be "neutralized" first.
	        Buildings of a base  
	        
	    </para>
	    <section>
	        <title>Advantages</title>
	    	<para>
	       		A neutral base provides several benefits to current controlling team:
	    	</para>
	    	<itemizedlist>
		        <listitem>
		            <para>
		                The base provides slight vision around the base.
		            </para>
		        </listitem>
		        <listitem>
		            <para>
		                Team mates will regenerate some portion of their health while staying in base without fighting.
		            </para>
		        </listitem>
		        <listitem>
		            <para>
		                Players can control siege machines and/or footmen that can be produced in that base.
		            </para>
		        </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
		    <title>Disadvantages</title>
		    <para>
		        To provide some team balance, holding neutral bases should have some negative aspects.
		    </para>
		    <itemizedlist>
		        <listitem>
		            <para>
		                Each base has at least two or three entrances.
		            </para>
		        </listitem>
		        <listitem>
		            <para>
		                Bases have no defence towers or something like this. You must defend them with your team.
		            </para>
		        </listitem>
		        <listitem>
		            <para>
		                Units spawned in that base cannot be moved or kept inside its centrum.
		            </para>
		        </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Player abilities</title>
	    <para>
	         Players can launch missiles to shoot enemies like in Counter Strike.
	    </para>
	</section>
</article>