<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Gameplay</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	
	<section>
		<title>Game setting and goal</title>
		<para>
			Two teams fight against on a large map. Each team consists of a
			maximum of 5 players. The first team that destroys enemy base wins.
			A single player mode is not planned.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>General game cycle</title>
		<para>
			Both teams start randomly at either top-left or bottom-right
			corner of map (yes, this is contrary to common multiplayer maps like
			LOL. That's intended.).
			Teams spread into the map trying to conquer
			neutral bases that are spread all over the map. Then they will move
			forward to enemy base.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Neutral bases</title>
		<para>
			Neutral bases can be conquered by a team. Once a base is conquered it should
			be defended against enemy team.
			If defence fails, enemy team can conquer the neutral base to optain its
			benefits.
		</para>
		<para>
			Neutral bases consist of a tower surrounded by some buildings. The tower
			provides some basic vision (see advantages) and is the central key of
			the base.
			A player can conquer a base by right-clicking its tower and channeling
			until control switched to his team. An already conquered base must be
			"neutralized" first.
			Buildings of a base can protect players because they block vision.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Advantages</title>
			<para>
				A neutral base provides several benefits to current controlling team:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Vision:</emphasis>
						The base provides slight vision around the base.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Regeneration:</emphasis>
						Team mates will regenerate some portion of their health while
						staying in base without fighting.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>More units:</emphasis>
						Players can control siege machines and/or footmen that can be
						produced in that base.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						(fma) <emphasis>Some kind of 'money':</emphasis> 
						Controlling a base should generate some kind of resource which
						can be used to buy units or do some other actions. The more bases
						you control, the more money you get.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Disadvantages</title>
			<para>
				To provide some team balance, holding neutral bases should have some
				negative aspects:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Backdooring:</emphasis>
						Each base has at least two or three entrances.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Vulnerability:</emphasis>
						Bases have no defence towers or something like this. You must
						defend them with your team.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>No defence:</emphasis>
						Units spawned in that base cannot be moved or kept inside its
						centrum, so they have to defend with their team itself.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Player abilities</title>
		<section>
		    <title>Shooting</title>
		    <para>
		        Players can launch missiles to shoot enemies like in Counter Strike.
		        (fma) The variety of available weapons may look like in Quake, where
		        each weapon feels very distinct to the others and serves another purpose.
		        The weapon balancing is much greater than in 'realistic' shooters like
		        Counter-Strike or Call Of Duty, in which all weapons feel more or less
		        the same. (/fma)
		    </para>
		</section>
		<section>
		    <title>Controlling units</title>
		    <para>
		        Once in a base, a player can choose to stay there for a while and control units <emphasis>instead of</emphasis> running around the map.
		        If he does so, he gains control over most units that spawn in that base. That might behave similar to Warcraft 3.
		        Players can use these units to ambush enemy team or fight forward towards their base. There are also some defensive units that can heal or chop trees down.
		    </para>
		    <para>
		        Players controlling units are not safe from attacks by enemies. Staying in a neutral base controlled by you can be dangerous due to vulnerability of these bases.
		        A player is not able to move or interact with his game-figure while controlling units. That makes unit-controlling risky.
		        To ensure survival, a team has to stick together and protect an ally that controls units.
		    </para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>