<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<articleinfo>
	    <title>Interface-Design</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
	    <title>Why is interface design so important?</title>
	    <para>
			The interface of a game is more important than you think! Providing control over the whole game and presenting information to the player
			it is one of the most important parts considering game design. It requires hard work to find a compromise between much control and a good overview.
			Overloading an interface is as useless as making it small and hard to read.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Functional requirements</title>
	    <para>
	         There are many requirements that an interface has to meet.
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Minimap:</emphasis> Important to keep track of game actions, a minimap is indispensable for a successful gameplay.
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Player information:</emphasis> Keep track of your health, munition and abilities helps to survival. 
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Interactive actionbar:</emphasis> An useful feature would be an interactive actionbar that is displayed context-dependent.
	                For example while controlling a neutral unit or fighting in your base you can display location-specific actions.  
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Graphical targets</title>
	    <para>
			The Interface should be clean but not too abstract. It's style should match the game's style.
			Graphics should not be too complicated to distract the user from game itself. Too small interface will keep off players with bad seeing capabilities.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Usability</title>
	    <para>
	        The interface doesn't only consists of the visual part of user interaction, there are also hidden things like keybindings, mouse interaction and so on.
	        This leads to an important point of gamer-friendlyness: individuality. A game with static possibilities to use is a silly game. A user wants to change
	        the way of interaction to his personal favourites. Some important features must not miss:
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Custom keybindings:</emphasis> Since games became faster and faster, custom keybindings became more popular, for example in World of Warcraft.
	                Allowing players to individualize their keybindings does integrate physically disabled people, too.
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Shut up, please:</emphasis> Sound is very important but also a very critical point of a game. At this point, we should distinguish between sound and music.
	                While music creates athmosphere and game feeling, sounds point out specific actions or notifications. A player should be able to set the balance between sound and music
	                to his own preference or even turn it off (there might come up situations where you don't want to wake up roommates...).
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    <section>
	        <title>What about us?</title>
	        <para>
	            Developers are really lacking in benefits from interface-design, so it should provide some features to improve development and bug-fixing.
	            Thus we need a bug-report tool that reports bugs automatically on the one hand, and let the user report bugs and problems ingame.
	            After being reported, bugs are autmatically put into our <ulink url="http://illonis.dyndns.org/pstatus/Eduras">bug-database</ulink>.
	        </para>
	    </section>
	</section>
</article>