<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<articleinfo>
	    <title>Interface-Design</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
	    <title>Why is interface design so important?</title>
	    <para>
			The interface of a game is more important than you think! Providing control over the whole game and presenting information to the player,
			it is one of the most important parts considering game design. It requires hard work to find a compromise between much control and a good overview.
			Overloading an interface is as useless as making it small and hard to read.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Functional requirements</title>
	    <para>
	         There are many requirements that an interface has to meet.
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Minimap:</emphasis> Important to keep track of game actions, a minimap is indispensable for a successful gameplay.
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Player information:</emphasis> Keep track of your health, munition and abilities helps to survival. 
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Interactive actionbar:</emphasis> An useful feature would be an interactive actionbar that is displayed context-dependent.
	                For example while controlling a neutral unit or fighting in your base you can display location-specific actions.  
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Game configuration:</emphasis> The player must have the ability to change some client settings to match his behaviour (see Usability).
	                In a multiplayer game, <ulink url="http://cdn.memegenerator.net/instances/400x/21402242.jpg">one cannot simply pause the game</ulink>, so settings changes must apply on-the-fly.
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Graphical targets</title>
	    <para>
			The Interface should be clean but not too abstract. It's style should match the game's style.
			Graphics should not be too complicated to distract the user from game itself but epic artwork style is epic.
			Too small interface will keep off players with bad seeing capabilities.
			But it is very important that players can recognize important facts like health and map position very fast.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	        It is a lot easier for players to learn the game if its interface is similar to common games. Considering popularity and first-play-enthusiasm the interface
	        should not matter. 
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Usability</title>
	    <para>
	        The interface doesn't only consist of the visual part of user interaction, there are also hidden things like keybindings, mouse interaction and so on.
	        This leads to an important point of gamer-friendlyness: individuality. A game with static possibilities to use is a silly game. A user wants to change
	        the way of interaction to his personal favourites. Some important features must not miss:
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Custom keybindings:</emphasis> Since games became faster and faster, custom keybindings became more popular, for example in World of Warcraft.
	                Allowing players to individualize their keybindings does integrate physically disabled people, too.
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Shut up, please:</emphasis> Sound is very important but also a very critical point of a game. At this point, we should distinguish between sound and music.
	                While music creates athmosphere and game feeling, sounds point out specific actions or notifications. A player should be able to set the balance between sound and music
	                to his own preference or even turn it off (there might come up situations where you don't want to wake up roommates...).
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>
	                <emphasis>Visual aids:</emphasis> Players with visual impairment may want to have a colorblind-mode with more contrast (like League of Legends). The ability
	                of changing the UI size may help users with higher resolutions to detect something on their map.
	            </para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    <section>
	        <title>Localization</title>
	        <para>
	            To make as many players as possible play this game, it is necessary to translate it into different languages. To achieve this big goal, we will use powerful
	            Java built-in capabilities (see <ulink url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/i18n/index.html">Java Trail: Internationalization</ulink>). It will be difficult
	            to provide several languages but at least we want to start with english (default language) and german. Community might help us later on to introduce more languages.
	        </para>
	    </section>
	    <section>
	        <title>What about us?</title>
	        <para>
	            Developers are really lacking in benefits from interface-design, so it needs to provide features to improve development and bug-fixing.
	            Thus we need a bug-report tool that reports bugs automatically on the one hand, and let the user report bugs and problems ingame.
	            After being reported, bugs are autmatically put into our <ulink url="http://illonis.dyndns.org/pstatus/Eduras">bug-database</ulink>.
	        </para>
	    </section>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Spectator mode</title>
	    <para>
	        Spectator mode is a two-sided sword: One the one hand it allows other players to join in and learn from other player's gameplay. They can view significant matches
	        and discuss about teamplay. On the other hand it provides a way to get information about your opponent. If there's communication between spectators and players, this
	        can lead to a big advantage in favour of a team.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	        A solution could be a similar behaviour to League of Legends where spectator view is delayed 3 minutes. In some exceptions, e.g. on tournaments, there could be an exception.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Game recording</title>
	    <para>
	        A very exciting feature is game recording. It allows a team to review their recent games, discuss failures and review group behaviour.
	        Due to recording mechanics, a recorded game requires only a small amount of memory as the game is not recorded as video file. Because of this players need to use their
	        game client to replay matches.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	        Replays bring a lot help for beginner players, too. They can watch replays that show advanced players to learn from their playstyle and moving behaviour.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>GUI-Elements</title>
	    <para>
	        In this section we collect all elements that are shown in the main GUI and their description.
	    </para>
	    <section>
	        <title>Overview</title>
		    <table>
		        <title>GUI-Elements and their properties that are shown when player has control over his hero.</title>
		        <tgroup cols="5">
		            <thead>
		                <row>
		                    <entry>
		                        Element
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Short description
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Display type
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Displayed values
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Possible positions
		                    </entry>
		                </row>
		            </thead>
		            <tbody>
		                <row>
		                    <entry>
		                        Minimap
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Shows visible portion of map and ally positions.
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        generated image
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Map background, visible players, fog of war, pings, bases
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        top-right, bottom-right, center-bottom or bottom-left
		                    </entry>
		                </row>
		                <row>
		                    <entry>
		                        Player stats
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Shows information about player status
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        health bar, int values, small icons
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        health, munitions, items
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        top-left, bottom-left, top-center
		                    </entry>
		                </row>
		                <row>
		                    <entry>
		                        Party
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Shows information about your party
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        icon, health bar 
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        profile picture, health 
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        left-center, vertical
		                    </entry>
		                </row>
		                <row>
		                    <entry>
		                        Chat
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Chatting with team mates or all-channel.
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Textbox
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        chat messages, important game events 
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        bottom-left
		                    </entry>
		                </row>
		                <row>
		                    <entry>
		                        Game stats
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        Displays game time, holded bases.
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        scoreboard
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        game time, count of holded bases
		                    </entry>
		                    <entry>
		                        top center, bottom center
		                    </entry>
		                </row>
		            </tbody>
		        </tgroup>
		    </table>
	    </section>
	    <section>
	        <title>Minimap</title>
	        <para>
	            The minimap is a small illustration of current map.
	            It shows several details that help orientating and locating other players and gaining overview about game situation:
	        </para>
	        <itemizedlist>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Your own base:</emphasis> Your own base at starting position is always visible. Enemy players inside it will be displayed on minimap.
	                    You will be noticed by alarm and ping when an enemy enters your base.
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Your camera position:</emphasis> Your current camera-position is surrounded by a clearly visible rectangle.
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Neutral bases:</emphasis> Neutral bases are indicated by small icons or dots even when they are not visible.
	                    Icons differ in color based on current holding team. 
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Team mates:</emphasis> Your team mates are displayed so you can identify who is where.
	                    Their vision is shared with you.
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Controlled units:</emphasis> Controlled units will be shown as simple dots. Their vision is shared with you.
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	        </itemizedlist>
	        <para>
	            Clicking on minimap will move your camera to clicked position. Using modifies you can ping different notifications to your team mates:
	        </para>
	        <itemizedlist>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Ctrl-Click:</emphasis> Ping to mark an attack position ("Attack here!").
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Alt-Click:</emphasis> Ping to mark a dangerous position ("Be careful over there!" or "Keep off there!").
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    <emphasis>Shift-Click:</emphasis> Ping to mark a where to gather ("Come here and wait!").
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	        </itemizedlist>
	        <para>
	            Right-clicking on map will start a player move to clicked position.
	        </para>
	    </section>
	    <section>
	        <title>Chat</title>
	        <para>
	            Game chat allows players to communicate with each other. Chat messages are marked with posting-time (either game time or real time) and posting player in following scheme:
	            <computeroutput>[14:38] Playername: Message</computeroutput>.
	            There is also possibility to chat with enemy team using All-chat. These message have a different color and are preponed with <computeroutput>[All]</computeroutput>.
	            Older chat messages will fade out (not completely) to provide a better view of the game world.
	            Game hoster can disable All-Chat before game starts (this cannot be changed ingame). Spectators are not able to view chat (optional) at all. 
	        </para>
	        <para>
	            <emphasis>Improved messaging using short-codes:</emphasis> Players can use keystrokes (Ctrl+1 to Ctrl+7) to send predefined chat messages to group chat.
	            These messages can be defined in client settings and are sent immediately without confirmation.
	        </para>
	        <para>
	            Some non-player messages are displayed in chat aswell. But it's important to keep amount of these messages low so communication is not disturbed.
	        </para>
	        <itemizedlist>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    A player disconnected/reconnected/quit.
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                    A team surrenders.
	                </para>
	            </listitem>
	        </itemizedlist>
	        <para>
                More events are displayed by other gui-elements.
            </para>
	    </section>
	</section>
</article>