<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Letz do this!</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Florian</firstname>
			<surname>Mai</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			We have been working on this project for over a year now,
			sometimes
			more focused and sometimes less.
			You can say that we have
			achieved a lot, if you take into account that
			we have not used any
			engines, frameworks and libraries
			besides the core Java libraries.
			Anyways, to get the whole project go
			seriously, to realize an
			innovative, exiting, enjoyable,
			attracting game experience, we would
			need to work on it full time. As illonis
			and Ren are going to graduate
			with bachelor's in September 2014, it
			is a good occasion to start
			working fulltime in fall 2014.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>How are we going to finance working full time??</title>
			<para>
				Good question! As we should not risk starving or becoming
				homeless due
				to a lack of money in our wallet, we would need to get
				some money from somewhere. The idea is to raise money on a
				crowdfunding
				platform like kickstarter or indiegogo. I think about
				30.000 Euro would be sufficient to keep two developers alive and
				finance
				additional hard- and software we would need to purchase.
				Any
				extra money can of course be invested to involve externals or hire
				further developers/specialists to speed up and improve the
				development. Unfortunately, I have no idea of the likelihood of
				raising so much money. But I think it's worth the try.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Why would someone invest in Eduras??</title>
			<para>
				Good question! I believe there are some critical factors we have to
				focus on to maximize money we can raise from other people.
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						Quality: Very important is to be able to present a
						prototype of Eduras
						that shows where the journey is going,
						what is
						special about Eduras and why it's worth to wait for and invest
						in
						it.
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						Quantity: No matter how good an Eduras prototype is: If
						nobody knows about
						it, nobody can spend money on it. We have
						to make
						sure that as many people as possible become aware that
						Eduras is
						out there and ready to go.
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						Vision: We need a precise idea of what we want to make in
						the future and
						present it in an exciting way.
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Realization</title>
		<section>
			<title>Timeline</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					01.01.2014 - Ingame chat, launcher/installer, UDP hole
					punching,
					bugtracker/forum
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					01.03.2014 - Rotating, rocket launcher, mines, assault
					rifle, flexible
					settings, ammunition, graphical distinction of
					objects, remote console
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					07.03.2014 - Start of closed beta, fix of major
					performance bottlenecks
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					13.03.2014 - Test event for deathmatch with closed beta
					participants.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					14.03.2014 - interactive mode spots, neutral bases,
					resources, vision
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					21.03.2014 - interactive-mode HUD, unit factory, spell
					factory, tech factory
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					01.04.2014 - heal-spell, star-unit, observer-unit,
					bomb-units, vision spell,
					tech-upgrades for units, spells, resources
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					07.04.2014 - conquer mode, map for conquer mode
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					10.04.2014 - Test event for conquer-mode with closed beta
					participants.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					07.05.2014 - two more maps for conquer-mode, one map for
					deathmatch
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					08.05.2014 - test event for new maps
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					01.06.2014 - spectator mode and spectator-bot server
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					01.06.2014 - start of main test phase with weekly test
					events / fix bugs and
					take feedback into account
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					15.08.2014 - end of main test phase / Eduras prototype
					should be more or less
					final
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					01.08.2014 - start advertising Eduras and Eduras
					tournament
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					01.09.2014 - Start of crowdfunding campaign / make Eduras
					prototype pulic
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					06.9. to 08.09.2014 - Eduras tournament
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					15.10.2014 - End of crowdfunding campaign
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>General approach to implementing tasks</title>
			<para>
				No matter what you do, you should always have on mind that
				we're
				implementing a prototype. If Eduras should really
				become a
				serious project next fall, we will have to rethink everything
				anyways because I believe that due to our small
				experience in game
				development many things will have to be started over. That
				means, for
				now, we should not focus on
				perfect software architecture but rather
				use dirty hacks if it's needed and
				speeds things up in the scope of
				our
				limited time
				window. For example, don't write documentation unless
				it's really critical in order to work with it. Consider
				that most
				likely no further developers will join our team
				until next year.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Features to implement for prototype</title>
			<para>The timeline seen above indicates what features to implement.
				Let me explain them more precisely here.</para>
			<para>The ingame chat, launcher and bug tracker are already there,
				but not all of them are working properly. The launcher / installer
				needs to be
				fixed with windows, the ingame chat has to be integrated
				and fixed too.
				The bug tracker should be made accessible on
				the Eduras
				website protected by an authentication mechanism (which is
				basically
				there already, too). The UDP hole punching is
				implemented, but
				doesn't
				work with some routers, we need to figure that out. We
				should
				get
				these issues solved before we
				start something new, because they
				are
				critical to potential beta
				testers.
			</para>
			<para>
				Rotation means the main figure's front should look towards the
				direction of the
				mouse pointer. Hitboxes should rotate
				simultaneously. Furthermore, missiles should be
				released at the tip
				of the
				figure's front (maybe a designated vertex)
				instead of
				arbitrarily
				"somewhere in front" of the
				figure.
			</para>
			<para>

			</para>
			<para>The rocket launcher's missiles are relativly slow. When they
				collide, they explode and make great damage not only to the
				hit
				target but also to objects in a certain area of effect.
			</para>
			<para>
				Mines are like rocket launcher missiles, but they dont move.
			</para>
			<para>
				An assault rifle is a weapon with very low damage, but
				infinitly high
				speed and low cooldown.
			</para>
			<para>
				Flexible settings means what is discussed in the 'Settings'
				document.
			</para>
			<para>
				Ammunition is of course what you think it is. When you shoot,
				your ammo
				decreases, when you collect a weapon, the ammo
				for that
				weapon increases by some number.
			</para>
			<para>
				It might be necessary to make objects better distinguishable
				from each
				other, for example weapons and missiles. We can do
				that in a
				very simple way by designing different shapes for weapons and
				assign
				them different colors. Don't spend to much
				time on real animations as
				we don't have it and it's not that critical
				to the game experience.
			</para>
			<para>
				The conquer-mode will basically be what is described in the
				'gameplay'
				document.
			</para>
			<para>
				Interactive mode spots are small designated areas where a
				player can switch
				from ego-mode to interactive-mode.
				It is usually in
				or close to a neutral base (or even the same). A
				neutral base is a
				designated area. If a player
				of your team stays in there for a
				certain amount of time without any
				player from another team coming in
				this area during
				that time, your team takes over control of that
				base.
			</para>
			<para>
				Each team has a shared 'resource' pool. There is only one
				resource and
				everything you do in interactive-mode you have
				to pay for
				with that resource. The resource pool increases over time.
				The more
				bases you control, the faster it grows.
				Additionally, for every
				player of the opponent's team that you kill, you gain
				some extra
				amount of resources.
			</para>
			<para>
				As players in interactive mode can scroll through the map
				freely and
				for this gamemode it is essential that you don't
				know what
				your opponent is doing, we need to implement some kind of
				vision. As
				a first approach, we can implement that
				every unit your team controls
				and every main figure provides vision in a
				circle around the unit as
				you know it from common
				RTS games.
			</para>
			<para>
				When a player is in interactive mode, he should have an
				RTS-like
				interface. That interface should show the current amount
				of
				resources, a mini-map to navigate through the map faster and
				a list
				of all the actions the player can perform in interactive mode. So
				there should be a
				tab for spells, unit production and tech upgrades
				each. There should be a shortcut for each
				action the player can
				perform. The unit factory is a physical object on the map where
				newly
				built units pop out. Tech and spell factory are meta terms for
				however you want to implement it. Also, the user should be able
				to
				assign hotkeys to groups of units or single objects dynamically.
			</para>
			<para>
				When using the heal spell, the user has to click an area in the
				map and
				all units in your team which
				are in that area are healed by
				some amount. Through tech upgrades you
				can increase the radius and
				effectivness
				of the heal spell. The vision spell provides vision for
				a few seconds in the
				area the user
				clicks on on the map. Through
				tech
				upgrades you can increase the duration and range of the vision
				spell. Observer units are small, very fast and
				cost extensive units
				that only provide vision but cannot do anything
				else. Bomb units are
				like rocket missiles, but you
				can control where they go. Star units
				are weak units, that can shoot.
				They don't shoot automatically, so
				the user has to
				trigger that manually. The units will shoot towards
				the point the user
				clicks on.
			</para>
			<para>
				In the prototype's spectator mode the spectator should be able
				to
				scroll freely as well as to follow a particular user. Furthermore
				the spectator shall be shown all the statistics that are available.
				To pull away all the traffic from the game server and thus avoid
				lags
				for the player, we will implement a spectator-bot-client, that
				connects
				to a game server as a spectator and forwards all the
				information
				to real spectators which connect to the spectator bot
				instead of to the
				game server.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Test events and test phase</title>
			<para>
				The beta test phase will start in March after we will have
				fixed
				most things
				that prevent a fluid and easy game experience and
				all the
				enviroment for testers is up and running. At that point of
				time, the
				performance should have been made good enough to enjoy the
				game
				without too much
				frustration due to lags or errors. We will run
				game
				servers 24/7 then so
				testers can play whenever they want.
				Furthermore, we will have
				designated test events where we invite 10 -
				15 people to play at the
				same time to watch the performance when
				there is big traffic. We can invite our friends as
				beta
				testers , I'm
				sure we will find enough among them, who like to
				play video games ;).
				They can give feedback directly
				to us or via the provided forum and
				bug trackers. We will encourage
				them to be as honest as possible and
				not care about our feelings. In
				June we will have a designated test
				phase that lasts about two
				months. By that date, all implementation
				should be finished. From
				then on, we will focus on fixing bugs and
				change/modify/add/remove
				whatever results from the feedback we get
				from our testers. That might involve
				balancing and even adding more
				weapons, units and spells if it turns out that
				the current
				functionality is not convenient enough. To address all the possible issues
				that might arise the test phase is as long as it is. After the test
				phase the
				prototype should be more or less final. That doesn't mean
				that we don't fix
				bugs if we still find some.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Advertising Eduras</title>
			<para>
				I believe it is really important to advertise your crowdfunding
				project very much in order for the people to
				spend money on it. I
				believe that we have to make some kind of a show out
				of the whole
				process. I have seen
				many projects whose basic idea was great but
				it was presented
				poorly. These project did not reach their
				goal. And I
				have seen projects that were rather boring but advertised
				like hell.
				These projects did not only
				reach their goal but also exceeded it by
				far.
			</para>
			<para>
				While we will not have spent much money on the Eduras project
				to this
				point of time, I think it will be necessary to
				invest some money now. The
				idea is to have an Eduras tournament with an
				attractive amount of
				prize money. The tournament
				would take place just a few days after
				the release of the prototype. Due
				to the fact that nobody can
				practise much because of the little time
				anyone can win and this
				will
				attract many people to participate in the tournament. Furthermore,
				people will experience the game and its idea under competitive
				conditions.
				To grab as much attention as possible, we can stream the
				whole tournament
				on a weekend and make a show out of it. On the
				stream we can advertise Eduras
				and the crowdfunding project very
				efficently as people directly see and hear what
				the project is about.
			</para>
			<para>
				Of course, before that we have to ensure that people are aware of the
				event. I think mass spams on social network
				and gaming websites will do the trick to point people to what we have
				to offer. The gaming community is very good at
				informing themselves and others, I believe.
			</para>
			<para>
				More important will be what we have to offer besides the tournament. We
				not only have to provide a lot of information but also
				present them in a rousing way. Maybe we should look for some professional
				help if this is not too expensive. A whole month from
				01.08 to 01.09 is scheduled time to figure that out.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Chances and Risks</title>
		<section>
			<title>Risks</title>
			<para>
				illonis and Ren are graduating in the end of September 2014. It's
				realistic, that they will not focus on their bachelor's thesis
				as much as they could and thus might get a worse grade than they could
				achieve under normal circumstances. But it's also true
				that if they continue studying for master's degree anyways, no one will
				give a shit on what grade they had in their bachelors degree.
				Another risk is that they might lose money. If the goal given in the
				crowdfunding campaign is not reached, they won't get anything
				in return to the effort made before. I think the total expenses will
				be about 2500 Euro, depending on how much we spend on prize money.
				We will need to rent several more servers to run Eduras on for a
				month which are about 80 Euro each. Additionally, we might need to
				hire
				some professionals to some marketing or legal (?) stuff for maybe about
				500-1000 Euro. I don't know how to make a more precise estimate.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Chances</title>
			<para>
				illonis and Ren are graduating in the end of September 2014. It is THE best
				occasion to start something own. If they don't reach the goal,
				they can simply keep on studying as nothing has happened but have made
				another experience. If they reach the goal but however things get
				screwed up later, they will have made A LOT of new experiences and
				can simply continue studying afterwards. But if things actually work
				out we will not only have got EVEN MORE EXPERIENCE but also made a
				dream come true.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Summary</title>
			<para>Besides some money we have nothing at all to lose.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>