<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>ShapeCreator</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jannis</firstname>
			<surname>Mell</surname>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>What's this about?</title>
		<para>
			In this chapter you will learn to use our powerful shapecreator tool.
			It allows easy creation and editing of shapes. Therefore, it supports
			you in any possible way: It provides a visual live preview, exact
			coordinate positioning, collision testing and a huge list of templates. 
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Handling the viewport</title>
		<para>
			The drawing panel on the right side is the central point of editing.
			You can see the final shape here and interact with your mouse.
		</para>
		<para>
			The panel allows you several ways to change your view on the shape:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Hold the right mouse button and drag the mouse to move
					the panel.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Dragging the viewport</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/shapecreator_drag.png" format="PNG" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Scroll the mouse wheel up to zoom in and down to zoom out.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can also press
					<computeroutput>CTRL-1, CTRL-2,..., CTRL-5</computeroutput>
					to directly	zoom to 1x, 2x, ... 5x zoom. Use
					<computeroutput>CTRL-+</computeroutput> to increase zoom
					by 0.5 and <computeroutput>CTRL--</computeroutput> to decrease
					by 0.5. To enter a custom zoom value, press
					<computeroutput>Z</computeroutput> and enter any custom value
					greater <computeroutput>0.1</computeroutput>.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Zooming the shape</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/shapecreator_zoom.png" format="PNG" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</listitem>		
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			You can go to <computeroutput>View -> Reset view</computeroutput> at
			anytime to reset the zoom and center the shape.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Editing the shape</title>
		<para>
			Editing shapes with the shapecreator is a very simple task. Make sure that
			your shapes match the shape criteria described later on so your shape will not
			blow up the game.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Edit modes</title>
			<para>
				Dragging vertices is possible in every mode.
				You can select a vertice by clicking on the table row or click on the shape
				edge (this is not available in delete mode).
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					Vertice table and viewport are synchronized.
				</para>
				<para>
					This means selecting a table row results in the correspondent vertice
					to be highlighted in the viewport. Coordinates are updated immediately, too!
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				There are provided two (actually three) editing modes to modify the shape.
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>Add vertices</emphasis> (Hotkey
					<computeroutput>A</computeroutput>)</para>
					<para>In this mode, you can click into the viewport to add a new
					vertice at the end of the list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>Select and drag</emphasis> (Hotkey
					<computeroutput>S</computeroutput>)</para>
					<para>
						This is kind of a no-mode that allows you to drag vertices
						and change the viewport without adding or deleting vertices.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>Delete vertices</emphasis> (Hotkey
					<computeroutput>D</computeroutput>)</para>
					<para>
						In this mode, you can click on existing vertices to remove
						them. This will result that the former and next vertice
						will be connected.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Criteria for a valid shape</title>
			<para>
				<emphasis>coming soon...</emphasis>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Shape files</title>
		<para>
			Shape files are rather simple. They just contain lines of vertices.
			Each line contains a single vertice, represented by x and y
			coordinates.
		</para>
		<para>
			An example shape file for a rectangle can be seen in the following example:
		</para>
		<programlisting>30,30
30,-30.53
-30,-30.53
-30,30</programlisting>
		<important>
			<para>
				Loading shape files into the game will be supported very soon.
			</para>
		</important>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Shape templates</title>
		<para>
			The shapecreator provides a template system that allows you to
			start creating a shape using a template.
			Simple templates are nothing else than a shape saved in a special format.
			There are parametrized templates, too. These allow the user to customize them before
			usage, for example using the circle template, users can specify radius and
			vertice count.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Create a template</title>
			<para>
				<emphasis>coming soon...</emphasis>
			</para>	
		</section>
	</section>	
</article>